Guide to the Mike Thornton Collection of Military Uniform Postcards circa 1915-1960 PR-408
New-York Historical Society
Mike Thornton collection of military uniform postcards
circa 1915-1960
New-York Historical Society
Thornton, Mike
PR-408
.66 Linear feet (approximately 177 postcards in 1 box).
Postcards showing uniforms worn by American, British, French, and Hessian regiments at Fort Ticonderoga during the Revolutionary War, and at the 1758 Battle of Ticonderoga. The collection includes views of 19th and 20th-century English and Scottish regimental uniforms, and the King's Guard / Queen's Guard at various London landmarks.
Arrangement
Postcards are sorted by topic, with American (colonial and Revolutionary-era) cards preceding those from Great Britain. The card sets showing various American, British, French, and Hessian regiments at Fort Ticonderoga bear sequential printing numbers, and so are sorted in order of publication. Captions have been transcribed as they appear on the cards.
Biographical note
Mike Thornton is Associate Curator of Material Culture at the New-York Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mike Thornton, 2017 (accession no. PPAC.2017.70).
Related Materials
Duplicate copies of the sets "American Troops at Fort Ticonderoga, 1775–1776–1777, by Colonel Harry C. Larter Jr., U.S.A.", "British Regiments, Ticonderoga, 1758–1777, by Alex. R. Cattley / The Royal Regiment of Artillery, Ticonderoga, 1758, 1759 and 1777", and "French Regiments Stationed at Fort Carillon (Fort Ticonderoga), July 8th, 1758, by Col. Harry C. Larter Jr., U.S.A." may be found in the New-York Historical Society Postcard Collection, PR-054, Sub-series II.A, Box 96-B.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists chiefly of linen era (circa 1930–1945) postcards depicting artistic renderings of uniforms worn by American, British, French, and Hessian regiments at Fort Ticonderoga during the Revolutionary War, and at the 1758 Battle of Ticonderoga. Artists include Harry C. Larter Jr. and Alex. R. Cattley. (So-called "linen" postcards were printed on inexpensive card stock with a finish that resembled linen fabric. They are easily recognizable by their texture and bright colors.) Beyond a handful of cards showing West Point cadets and a U.S. Army musician from the Civil War, the collection includes views of various 19th and 20th-century English and Scottish regimental uniforms, and of the King's Guard / Queen's Guard at Buckingham Palace, Whitehall, and the Tower of London.
Separated Materials
Two stereoscopic view cards that came with the collection, depicting buildings in London and Florence, have been transferred to the New-York Historical Society's Stereograph File, PR-065.
Fort Ticonderoga (N.Y.); Great Britain -- Army; Military uniforms; Ticonderoga, Battle of, N.Y., 1758; United States. Continental Army -- Uniforms; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; Postcards.
- United States. Fort Ticonderoga. American Troops, [1930-1945] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  "American Troops at Fort Ticonderoga, 1775–1776–1777, by Colonel Harry C. Larter Jr., U.S.A."
  • Major, 3rd New Jersey Regt., Field Officer of the Day (2)
  • Color Sergeant, 2nd New Hampshire, Poor's (2)
  • Captain of the Guard, 14th Conn. Regt., Burrell's (2)
  • Drummer, 2nd Canadian Regt., Congress's Own (2)
  • Sergeant of Marines, from 1st Penna. Bn. (2)
  • Matross, New York Artillery Company, Lambs (2)
  • Scout, 6th Continentals, Mass., Whitcomb's Rangers (2)
  • Private, 3rd Yorkers, Ulster Regt. (2)
  • Green Mountain Ranger, Warner's Regt. (2)
  • Fifer, 1st New York Regt., McDougall's (2)
  • Corporal, 6th Penna. Bn., Irvine's (2)
  • Rifleman, 4th Penn. Bn., Wayne's (2)
- United States. Fort Ticonderoga. British Regiments (2 folders), [1930-1945] (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  "British Regiments, Ticonderoga, 1758–1777, by Alex. R. Cattley / The Royal Regiment of Artillery, Ticonderoga, 1758, 1759 and 1777"
  • Grenadier Company Soldier, 47th Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 34th Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 24th Regiment (2)
  • Gunner, Royal Regiment of Artillery (1)
  • Officer, 29th Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 33rd Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Corporal, 53rd Regiment (2)
  • Private, The Royal Highland Regiment, The 42nd (The Black Watch) (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 31st Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 62nd Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Serjeant [sic], 24th Regiment (2)
  • Officer, 20th Regiment (2)
  • Private of the Light Company, 46th British Regiment (2)
  • Private, 60th Foot (Royal Americans) (2)
  • Soldier, 26th Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Corporal, 9th Regiment (2)
  • Battalion Soldier, 20th Regiment (2)
  • Grenadier, 21st Regiment (Royal North British Fuziliers) (2)
  • Private, British Infantry, at the End of the American Revolution, 1783 (2)
  • Private, The Royal Highland Regiment, The 42nd (The Black Watch), at the End of the American Revolution, 1783 (2)
- United States. Fort Ticonderoga. French Regiments, [1930-1945] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  "French Regiments Stationed at Fort Carillon (Fort Ticonderoga), July 8th, 1758, by Col. Harry C. Larter Jr., U.S.A."
  • 72nd Béarn Regiment (1)
  • 34th La Sarre Regiment (1)
  • French General Officer, 1758 (1)
  • 47th Royal Corps of Artillery, 1758 (1)
  • 37th Royal Roussillon Regiment (2)
  • 44th Royal La Marine Regiment (1)
  • 24th La Reine Regiment (2)
  • 71st Berry Regiment (1)
  • 53rd Languedoc Regiment (1)
  • Officer of the Royal Engineers, 1758 (1)
  • Canadian Militia (1)
  • 68th Guyenne Regiment (1)
- United States. Fort Ticonderoga. Hessian Regiments, [circa 1945] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  [Hessian Regiments at Fort Ticonderoga by Colonel Harry C. Larter, U.S.A.]
  • Brunswick Jaegers (von Barner), 1777 (1)
  • Grenadier Noncommissioned Officers (Erbprinz, von Riedesel, Prinz Friedrich), 1776 (1)
  • Brunswick Infantry Regiment (von Rhetz), 1776–77 (1)
  • Hesse-Hanau Infantry (Erbprinz), 1776 (1)
  • Brunswick Infantry (Prinz Friedrich), 1776 (2)
  • Brunswick Infantry Regiment (von Specht), 1776–1777 (1)
  • Grenadiers (von Rhetz, von Riedesel, von Specht), 1777 (1)
  • Brunswick Infantry (von Riedesel), 1776 (1)
  • Brunswick Light Infantry Battalion (von Barner), 1777 (1)
  • Hesse-Hanau Artillery, 1777 (1)
  • Winter Clothing Issued to the Brunswick & Hesse-Hanau Troops (Musketeer, Dragoon, Cannoneer) in Canada, 1776–77 (1)
  • Brunswick Dragoons (Prinz Ludewig), 1777 (1)
- United States. Fort Ticonderoga. General views, [1930-1945] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  • Aerial view (1)
  • Entrance to Place D'Armes, South Barracks (2)
  • Ethan Allen Stairway, West Barracks (2)
  • Sally Port and West Demilune (1)
  • South Platform (2)
  • South Platform in Winter (1)
  • Monument to the British and Colonial Regiments (2)
  • General Montcalm Congratulating his Victorious Troops, July 8, 1758 (3)
  • West Demi-Lune (1)
  • Portrait of George Washington (1)
- United States. West Point, [1945-1960] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Cadets, flag, cannon, and a portrait of Thomas Jefferson (5 cards).
- United States. Miscellaneous, [1930-1945] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes views of the first naval officer's training school, Boston; a U.S. Army musician, artillery, Civil War; the interior of Reynolds Tavern, 1737, as transformed into the Annapolis, Maryland public library; and the development of the American flag (8 cards).
- Great Britain. England. King's Guard / Queen's Guard, [circa 1915, 1955] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  At Buckingham Palace, Whitehall, Tower of London, etc.
- Great Britain. England. Various regiments, [circa 1915, 1960] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  • Duke of Cambridge's Own (Middlesex Regiment) (2 versions)
  • Worcestershire Regiment (1)
  • Suffolk Regiment (1)
  • Royal Sussex Regiment (1)
  • South Wales Borderers (2 versions)
  • Royal Irish Regiment (1)
  • Duke of Wellington's (West Riding Regiment) (1)
  • Border Regiment (1)
  • Loyal North Lancashire Regiment (1)
  • 1st King's Dragoon Guards at Dettingen, 1743 (1)
  • British Artilleryman of 1757 (2)
- Great Britain. Scotland (postcards issued by Elms Publishing Co.), [circa 1915] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  • Scots Guards (2)
  • Royal Scots Greys, 2nd Dragoons (3 types)
  • 1st, Royal Scots (1)
  • 21st, Royal Scots Fusiliers (1)
  • 25th, King's Own Scottish Borderers (1)
  • 26th, Cameronians (1)
  • 42nd, Black Watch (2 types)
  • 71st, Highland Light Infantry (2 types)
  • 72nd, Seaforth Highlanders (2 types)
  • 75th, Gordon Highlanders (2 types)
  • 79th, Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders (2 types)
  • 91st, Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders (3)
- Great Britain. Scotland (postcards issued by Valentine & Son), [circa 1915] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  • Gordon Highlanders (2)
  • Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders (2)
  • Seaforth Highlanders (1)
  • Black Watch Royal Highlanders (1)
  • Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders (2)